[theme music plays]
-[frogs croaking]
-[birds chirping]
-[sword slicing]
-[body thudding]
-[slicing continues]
-[thudding continues]
[sword slicing]
In kung fu, we say...
"One hand lies...
[both grunting]
[groans]
...the other hand tells the truth."
[Marco] Try that again.
If you, one day,
make it back to the West...
what will you tell men
of this strange word, "kung fu"?
Will you tell them that it means to fight?
Or will you say...
like a monk from Shaolin...
[inhales sharply]
to summon the spirit...
of the crane and the tiger?
[groans]
[panting]
Kung fu.
It means, "supreme skill from hard work."
[Hundred Eyes]
A great poet has reached kung fu.
The painter, the calligrapher...
they can be said to have kung fu.
Even the cook,
the one who sweeps steps...
or a masterful servant...
can have kung fu.
Practice. Preparation...
endless repetition.
Until your mind is weary,
and your bones ache.
Until you're too tired to sweat...
too wasted to breathe.
[groans]
That is the way, the only way...
one acquires kung fu.
[grunting]
Unfortunately, boy...
you have not.
A more fearsome army, I have never seen!
It is no wonder the barbarians fled.
[soldiers yelling in Mandarin]
[speaking English]
Yet...
it has come to the attention
of your Chancellor...
that some of his soldiers have questioned
the political order of the Song court...
now that the Emperor
has passed beyond our world.
General.
Who is the most supreme fighter
within your ranks?
Yang Chun.
In Shantung Province, he is known as...
"Whirlwind Tiger."
He has mastered the
Five Animal Styles of Shaolin.
May Song dynasty endure 10,000 years!
What do the men say about your
Cricket Minister's praying mantis games?
With humility and respect...
some have spoken of
the Chancellor's insect games as a...
curious hobby.
Those were the only words whispered,
My Chancellor.
Demonstrate...
why the name Whirlwind Tiger is so famous.
Defeat me,
and you are promoted to a command post
with all its residual income
and pleasures.
However... should I defeat you...
you are my chamber boy.
[yelling]
-[bones cracking]
-[screaming]
Praying Mantis Kung Fu.
Curious little hobby?
[neck snapping]
Ariq was my brother.
But he was a traitor.
Now, he is dead.
I took his head,
soaked the earth with his blood...
I loved him as a brother,
but I killed him as a traitor.
In my heart and by our laws...
I know this to be necessary and just.
Those who disagree with my actions,
speak now without repercussion.
That is the last
we shall speak of my brother.
Cousin Kaidu will inherit his lands,
his armies, his people.
Now...
as to the war deferred
with the Song rebels...
We were dishonored
at the Battle of Wuchang.
We must visit hell
upon the Cricket Minister.
With respect to my cousin, Jingim...
the Khan must now assert his dominion.
Our forces?
With Karakorum's men
finally standing ready...
-you are two armies strong.
-Three.
The armies of the West
are prepared for battle, Great Khan.
We await your command.
I have much to think on.
[Kaidu] Great Khan...
Tomorrow evening,
at my encampment, if I may...
I invite you to a feast...
in your honor.
[chuckling]
I will attend, Kaidu.
Thank you.
[door opening]
A tribute from the Song Chancellor,
Great Khan.
[flies buzzing]
How many Song prisoners
did we take at Wuchang?
[Jingim] A mere dozen, Father.
[court murmuring]
Rip their bodies asunder, Sire.
Send Sidao their parts.
[Kublai] My Minister of Finance,
identify these brave warriors.
See their families receive
tribute from the treasury.
That is your place.
It will be done, Sire.
[goats bleating]
[Nima] To service the Khan
is not merely an honor...
it is a blessing.
To be sure, those who satisfy the
Lord Khan's carnal needs here on Earth...
will be granted supreme favor
in the next life.
As well as 20 karats of gold.
You will be tested
by the royal concubines.
The most proficient in the art of arousal
will earn the privilege
of residing permanently here...
in our Great Khan's
Hall of Five Desires.
By "permanently,"
I mean just that.
If selected, you will remain
in the Hall of Five Desires
until released from royal service.
If you are chosen
to become a Royal Concubine...
all needs will be met.
Those not chosen will be delivered
to the Ministry of Finance
to be sold off to the Khan's court.
Those unclaimed by the court will be
sold to whorehouses in outer Cambulac.
Perform as though
your life depends upon it.
It most likely does.
[boisterous chatter]
Horseman. Sit.
I'm in a hurry.
I said sit.
Business done quickly
is business done badly.
Do you want me to do bad business, hmm?
There.
Eyeball to eyeball.
Now, we can either deal...
or fuck.
Your choice.
Your loss.
It's opal and silver.
And?
Last time, you gave me twice that.
I had bad month.
Hold, Europa.
What's your business here?
I'm a customer with coin.
Let me pass.
[Altan] Hey.
Where is the man
who owns the bay gelding outside?
Go ask the horse, Latin.
[Marco grunting]
The grassland was
sweet and cool tonight, Za Bing.
So much like my old home.
And so much like his.
What treasure
did you leave for him this night?
You know better than to ask.
My ignorance is not deep enough
to protect me.
And I do not trust the scoundrel
to protect you.
Tulga would not hurt me.
As long as the jewels come.
As long as he harbors hope to be with me.
That tether will weaken, Kokachin.
And he will expose you.
This must stop.
Whom do you serve?
We speak of this no more.
And you have nothing to fear.
That is precisely what I am bid to do.
Fear.
I must protect you.
And as you protect me...
I will protect you,
Za Bing.
You're my only friend in this world.
[Ling Ling singing in Mandarin]
[speaking English]
Sunflower?
Where is your servant?
Attending to my breakfast.
Excellent. Enjoy.
[Ling Ling continues singing]
[wine pouring]
[sighing]
Why would he summon me?
My suspicion?
Yes?
Is that you will discover
the answer to your question...
rather soon.
Perhaps you might lend your
venerable insight to another query.
I would rather enjoy my wine.
The Bayaut tribe. Who are they?
I grasp the spirit of your question.
Tread carefully, Master Polo.
Her parents, siblings, countrymen...
they were slaughtered
for refusing to bend to the Khan's will.
The Blue Princess is the last of her clan.
How did she survive?
Her royal blood is valued.
She is destined to be sold
for political currency.
Steer your eyes from her visage.
She is beyond your reach.
So I've been told.
You called for me, Sire?
[Kublai] Do you have brothers?
I wish I had.
Someone to play with.
Someone to conspire with.
Brothers...
Sometime blessing, sometime curse.
Like those in your holy book.
Cain and Abel?
Tell me of them.
Sons of Adam.
Cain was the first man to be born.
Abel, the first to die.
By the blade of his brother, yes?
Envious of God's love for Abel,
Cain killed his brother,
concealed his body...
and lied to the Lord above.
What became of the murderer?
He bore the mark of Cain...
and was cursed to roam the Earth.
Endlessly.
To this day?
No. He wandered until
he could wander no more.
So, he took a wife, built a house...
and lived there until it collapsed
and crushed him dead.
Some say this is an invented story,
nothing more.
Meant to impart a greater lesson.
Which is?
The scholars and historians
of Venice are superior
to all others across the land.
I have not the studies
to begin to explore such questions.
Try.
It is in our nature to seek
our brother's possessions.
And be willing to destroy to obtain them.
Superior to all others, hmm?
I did not mean to offend--
You shall attend
my cousin Kaidu's feast tonight.
I await your thoughts on a lesser culture.
Six of them?
[Ahmad] The youngest was 16.
Maidar's boy. Taban.
Taban. [sighs]
How many times had I told Maidar...
he was not prepared for war.
Like you, as a boy,
his head was always in numbers.
-And now it's in a thatched trunk.
-[woman moaning]
[scoffs] Ahmad. Please.
-My apologies, Empress.
-[sighs]
[moaning continues]
Send Maidar a purse of silver.
It is done.
The Khan commanded gold.
[moaning intensifies]
[Ahmad] Impressive.
I will not choose my husband's concubines
based upon Shria's judgment.
I've seen her faint
when a puppy licked her face.
[Ahmad] Well...
that's no puppy.
[Chabi] Have you already
taken tally, Ahmad?
Perhaps you'll add that one to your harem
before selling
the castoffs to the brothels?
[Ahmad] Whatever turns profits
for the Khan and fills a treasury...
I will oversee.
As is your duty.
[Ahmad]
Yes.
But not why I come to you.
I know it's not my place, and...
I do not wish to overstep my bounds.
You are as a son to the Khan and to me.
You need not hold your tongue.
Have you any insight
into the Khan's private thoughts?
Concerning?
Spilling the blood of that savage,
Jia Sidao.
Hatred does not cease by hatred.
But it may be stopped by a saber.
Until they eventually
turn the saber back on you.
Are these matters of finance, Ahmad?
Finance fuels the crucible of war...
and its spoils fill our treasury.
They are one and the same.
Why speak of this to me?
Why not Yusuf?
The Khan's ear opens widest
for you, Empress.
[Shria continues moaning]
You are a magician.
You are certain to be selected.
[Nima] Report to the Hall of Purification
for cleansing.
Stop.
Lift up your hair.
Sit.
When did you meet Ling?
I held her on her third day.
How did you come to know my sister?
You whored together.
Mei Lin was my friend.
Chancellor.
Do you enjoy your current station in life?
As concubine?
Yes... Chancellor.
You may speak freely.
I do, Chancellor.
It seems to me
that yours is the work of animals.
I see no worth in it,
as it speaks to our most base instincts.
But I suppose some in life must make do
with the meager skills
birth has bestowed upon them.
I make no judgment, of course.
You are quite stunning.
I never took notice.
Providence is upon you.
Your days will not be spent pinned
beneath stinking flesh on the floor.
You are to report every morning
to my sister's chambers
to care for my niece.
What you do with your nights
is entirely of your choosing.
You are excused.
[Chabi] No.
How old?
Nineteen.
What of this one's family?
Her father works in
the salt mines beyond the Wall.
And her?
Father died at Wuchang, Empress.
Before that?
He was a potter.
Not you.
You.
No, Empress, please, you must--
"Must"?
That is all for the Khan.
Take them to be dressed.
[Yusuf] Do you attend the feast?
My head and my heart
do not yearn for airag this evening.
Are you unwell, Sire?
A complicated answer
to a simple question.
Prince Jingim will stand proxy.
[groans]
What do you make of the boy?
As heir?
No, not that one.
The Latin.
He appears... insightful...
Passionate... reckless.
Time will determine
if he will be of use to the Khanate.
Hmm.
Good night.
[horse neighing]
Greetings.
Welcome, cousin.
We've slaughtered 20 pigs, 30 goats,
and a dozen antelope for the fire...
prepared wine and nermel for days.
When does the Khan's party arrive?
My men are ready to commence.
Pour the drink.
To begin before the Khan arrives
would be a great dishonor.
The Lord Khan
had other matters to attend to?
Hobbled by gout...
he sends his regrets, and me in his stead.
Then let us honor the General
who led our warriors at Wuchang.
May I take your horse, Master Polo?
[laughing]
[Kublai groaning]
Arrows and sabers, I can withstand.
But the gout...
it's a curse from the Eternal Blue Sky.
[Chabi] That...
-and an excess of wine.
-Yeah...
So much tension, husband.
Grandfather appeared to me whilst I slept.
Urged me to walk the kingdom with him...
and gout wouldn't let me take a step.
Genghis laughed at me.
He went off on his own.
The Great Genghis
did not have a brother like Ariq.
A Khan has no qualms or regrets.
Ahmad spoke to me.
He thinks war is the answer.
Why does Ahmad speak to you of war?
He is a trusted minister.
I am his Queen.
He has much doubt
his Khan will make the true decision.
He wanted to use you to sway my mind.
Well, he clearly came to the wrong person.
[Kublai] Hmm.
I should feed his balls to feral cats.
-[laughs]
-He takes liberties with his station.
He defends you
and wants only the best for you.
[sighs deeply]
He worries what may come
in the wake of Ariq's death.
You counseled me to kill my brother.
I did and I did it well.
Now, you must consider
all roads before you.
But the journey must not linger
in the deliberation.
I can only assume you have an opinion
as to which road must be taken.
[groaning loudly]
Choose wisdom over wrath.
Heal any rifts within yourself,
your armies, your people.
The Walled City will continue to stand...
only to fall at a time of your choosing.
[Khutulun] I have heard much of you.
Marco... Polo.
What does that mean?
"The Great Explorer."
No.
I think it means...
"Pale Flower."
"Flower"?
You look...
delicate to the touch.
I have killed hundreds of men in battle.
I didn't say the Pale Flower
didn't have thorns.
Sharper than a Mongolian's arrow.
Should I be afraid?
Only if you insult me.
Then...
I must watch my words.
And the women you have conquered.
Did they melt in your hands?
Like snow in the desert.
Take me in your hands.
[laughs]
Not that.
Do you wrestle in Venice?
Of course.
Show me.
-I don't want to hurt you.
-Oh. Mmm?
[chuckles]
[Khutulun laughs softly]
[Marco grunts]
[Khutulun panting]
[Hundred Eyes]
If the Gods are always watching...
we might as well put on a good show.
The inability to sleep
is the curse of the aged...
and the guilty.
And the gout-stricken.
Pardon me.
I foolishly assumed
you were dreaming about
your brother's head rolling in the dirt...
his body, a feast for vultures.
[Kublai] Do they hate me?
[Hundred Eyes] It is better to be
hated for what you are
than to be loved for what you are not.
You're a drunken fool.
So, kill me.
I have thought about it.
But you wish to sleep.
I know you want to tell me
one of those endless stories
from that infernal
Chinese teacher of yours.
No stories tonight, Sire.
No Zen riddles?
I will offer a truth instead.
Had you spared Ariq...
you would have encouraged other traitors.
His execution was just.
No. But it was necessary...
in that moment,
to preserve your Empire.
You ease one worry,
but aggravate one greater.
As life is wont to do.
[Byamba] Open your mouth!
[Marco] No, no, no, no, no.
-Open it!
-No, no!
[chuckles] Shut it!
[men laughing]
[Marco coughing]
[Kaidu] Tell us, Marco.
Do your feasts compare to this?
They are different.
[Byamba]
Here, we eat the pig.
In Venice, they dance with it.
If the Venetian feasts were comparable,
why would our friend leave home?
We wear masks.
For what purpose?
The mask frees us of inhibitions.
[Ahmad] And the butcher
beds the merchant's daughter...
while his wife beds the gardener.
The mask prevents embarrassment.
[Kaidu] Interesting.
Perhaps, some of our generals
should wear masks in the future.
To prevent embarrassment.
We have the greatest generals in the world
and all of history.
We would have been victorious at Wuchang
had Genghis Khan
or our Lord Kublai commanded.
[Byamba] I prefer a general
with aggression in his blood
to one who quakes with trepidation
on his steed.
I prefer a pure general.
A Mongol, raised Mongol...
bathed in the blood spilt by Genghis,
steeped in his ways.
A warrior like you, Byamba.
Untainted.
A true Mongol.
A man.
[crowd exclaiming]
Or woman.
[crowd chanting]
Has the Khan heeded our counsel?
Our Khan has a will of his own.
It is a will that may break
if he fails to act.
We will support and reinforce his will,
whatever it might be.
[Kaidu] Of course, Minister.
I would never suggest otherwise.
He is my Khan.
[soldiers yelling]
[crowd exclaiming]
Khutulun has grown more fierce with age.
And more beautiful.
It appears my daughter
will never take a husband!
-Daughter?
-She is a prized warrior...
whose virginity is promised
to any man who can defeat her.
Suitors abound,
offering horses by the score
for an opportunity to wrestle and win her.
My herds have multiplied, but...
I will find Khutulun her match.
You should challenge her, Byamba.
You are a powerful warrior.
I am not worthy, Kaidu.
Imagine if Khutulun
had commanded our armies at Wuchang.
A glorious victory
she would have given our Lord.
We are one wrestler short, Prince.
Care to test your skills?
Show us the...
aggression in your blood?
[Marco] I would be honored...
Lord Kaidu.
[laughs]
[crowd cheering]
[crowd chanting]
[both grunting]
[man groaning]
[crowd exclaiming]
[grunting]
[crowd chanting]
Son.
Am I?
I doubt the Great Khan
would humiliate his one true heir.
No, the Khan wouldn't
shame his one true son
by leaving him to attend a feast
with a Latin and a bastard whose--
[Jingim] Go on!
Kill me.
[sighs]
When my uncle, Ögödei,
became gravely ill...
the healers and shamans...
thought they could appease the spirits...
by sacrificing goats, boars and stags.
But Ögödei's illness just grew worse.
So, they tried offering women...
beggars and peasants.
Nothing.
Then men from the court.
Still, his illness increased.
And soon, when he was at death's door...
his most trusted shaman determined that...
the only way to cure him was...
to sacrifice a member of his family.
My father, Tolui...
volunteered.
He drank from the poisoned cup
and when he died...
Ögödei rose from his bed.
That, son, was a tale
conjured to save Tolui's face.
Losing face.
Chinese concept you've been taught...
and have experienced.
Truth is... Father was a weak man.
Screwing whores
and drinking airag till his liver burst.
He never deserved to
occupy the Mongol throne.
Honor...
he had none.
Courage...
he spent it at the gaming houses.
I still hear his whining in my ear.
You, too, whine like a woman.
A man who would be Khan
must stand tall and crush those
who dare mock him.
[Jingim] You don't see?
If I whine like a woman...
it is because you molded me that way.
They mock me because I think Chinese...
because I act Chinese!
Because you made me Chinese--
You were taught by Chinese scholars.
That does not make you less Mongol.
You act it...
or I will kill you.
[gasps]
I hear he has hundreds of consorts.
I hope he has thousands.
Being mounted once a year
is more than enough for me.
[softly] Daiyu says his cock
is like that of a horse.
[Changyang]
Then feed it oats and leave me alone.
[chuckles]
[gasps]
[Kublai] A ladle?
Your cousin said it was made by
the greatest artisan in India.
From the ball sack of an elephant.
Perhaps it is meant to be ornamental.
And?
What were your thoughts
on true Mongol culture?
How was the airag?
It was enjoyable.
Is that the only word you can conjure?
Highly enjoyable.
Hmm.
[grunts]
How did they speak of me?
With respect.
Befitting one of your magnitude.
Hmm.
And my son?
Did they afford him similar esteem?
He was shown the honor
due the son of the Great Khan.
Describe for me what you saw, Latin...
as you saw it.
A lie...
can cost innocent lives.
A lie about how the House of Ögödei...
treats the son of Kublai...
endangers this entire Empire!
Such lies should be punished.
[Marco] No.
Sire, no!
[grunting]
[panting]
Well, if I let him walk away,
he will have his wine
six nights from now and say...
"Khan was lied to by a lowly foreigner
and gave that liar his leave."
He shares your sin now.
He is your scapegoat.
Go, Latin.
Sleep off the drink.
[panting]
[kissing and panting]
[hissing]